Guide to the National Story Project Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
National Story Project Records
1998-2002.
Auster, Paul, 1947-
7.5 linear ft. (6 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1559
7268954
A collection of over 5,000 true short stories written as submissions for National Public Radio's (NPR) National Story Project, which was a segment on Weekend All Things Considered. The National Story Project was created and supervised by American author, Paul Auster.
Historical Note
The National Story project began in 1999 after American author, Paul Auster, read a selection from his novel Timbuktu on NPR's Weekend All Things Considered. Auster was asked to return to the program by its then host, Daniel Zwerdling, to perform another reading at a future date. Auster answered with the conditional response that he would be willing to return, but only if he could read other people's stories and not just his own.
The National Story Project began taking submissions from listeners in 1999 October through both e-mail and mail. The guidelines for the stories were that they had to be no more than three pages in length and that the submissions relayed a true event. The selected stories would then be edited or rewritten, if needed, by Auster and his team. The National Story Project aired on Weekend All Things Considered the first Saturday of each month from 1999 November until 2001 July and during that time received over 5,000 submissions from all over the United States on a wide variety of topics and from people of varying ages, gender and backgrounds.
After the National Story Project ended, Auster selected his favorite submissions and compiled them for a book entitled I Thought My Father Was God: And Other True Tales from NPR's National Story Project. The collection was published in 2002 by Picador, a Macmillan Publishing imprint.
Scope and Content
This collection contains over 5,000 submissions to the National Story Project, a program that aired from 1999 November until 2001 July on National Public Radio's Weekend All Things Considered. The collection primarily contains printed e-mail submissions and letters received through the mail. In addition to the stories, some participants sent cassette tapes or CDs of themselves reading their stories or performing music to accompany the submission. Also included are books, photographs, newspapers, magazines, pamphlets and other materials either meant to verify their submission as true, add context to their submission, or to show other formats that their submissions had appeared in previously.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 2 series
Series I: E-mail Submissions to the National Story Project, 1998-2001
Series II: Mailed Submissions to the National Story Project, 1999-2002
Subjects
National Public Radio (U.S.).; National Story Project (U.S.).; Weekend all things considered (Radio program).; Auster, Paul, 1947-; United States--Biography--Anecdotes.; United States--Social life and customs--20th century--Anecdotes.; Oral history.; Storytelling.; Short Stories.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Paul Auster Gift 11/30/2002
- Series I: E-mail Submissions to the National Story Project, 1998-2001
  This subseries contains print outs of National Story Project submissions that were entered electronically through e-mail.
  - 1998-1999 December (Box 1)
  - 1999 December-2000 August (Box 2)
  - 2000 August-2001 August, Undated (Box 3)
- Series II: Mailed Submissions to the National Story Project, 1999-2002
  This subseries contains National Story Project submissions that were entered by mail. These submissions contain stories as well as accompanying materials such as audio cassette tapes, CDs, photographs, newspapers, magazines, and other types of materials.
  - 1999 (Box 4)
  - 2000 January-July (Box 5)
  - 2000 August-2002 July (Box 6)
  - Undated (Box 6)
  - NPR Internal Correspondence